"Pros and Cons of Raw Food Diets"
Is it better to eat
our vegetables raw or cooked?
If you're thinking raw,
you're right!
But if you guessed cooked,
you're also right.
A number of nutrients,
like vitamin C,
are partially destroyed
by cooking.
On the other hand,
some nutrients,
like lycopene in tomatoes,
become more absorbable
upon cooking.
So, I advocate eating
a combination
of cooked and raw foods.
Check out this study
on long-term raw foodists.
This study was done in Europe,
so the "average Western diet"
here wasn't terrible,
about four servings
of fruits and vegetables a day;
versus a better so-called
"wholesome nutrition" diet
of seven daily servings
of fruits and veggies,
both raw and cooked;
versus a raw food diet,
in which they ate, on average,
a whopping 17 servings
of fruits and veggies a day,
leading them to have
about three times
the beta-carotene intake
compared
to the "average" eaters.
But that's intake.
How much of it actually
got into their bloodstreams?
Blood beta-carotene
is considered to be
a surrogate marker for
fruit and vegetable consumption.
Some researchers even suggest
if you tell them what your
blood beta-carotene level is,
they can tell you
what your health risk is.
So, who had the most
beta-carotene in their bodies?
Those eating 4 servings a day,
7, or 17?
It was the middle group--
the 7 daily servings group--
because cooking can boost
the absorption of phytonutrients
like beta-carotene.
For example,
you get more beta-carotene
in your bloodstream
eating cooked carrots
than you do eating
the same amount of raw carrots.
The raw foodists were eating
17 servings a day
and basically had the same
amount of this phytonutrient
reaching their internal organs
as those on the standard diet
getting 4 measly daily servings.
Raw diets can be better than
junky vegan diets because
they're free of processed foods,
like potato chips
and sugary drinks.
I couldn't find
any good evidence
raw diets are superior to whole
food, plant-based diets, though.
A dietary survey of 141
so-called
Hallelujah vegetarians,
following a mostly raw,
pure vegetarian diet,
found their raw food diets were
deficient in energy, protein,
and vitamins B12 and D, calcium,
selenium, and zinc.
A more recent survey
of strict raw food eaters
disturbingly found only
about half were supplementing
with vitamin B12
and were suffering
the consequences,
elevated levels of the toxic
metabolite homocysteine.
Most eating
the average Western diet
are getting
way too many calories,
but strict raw-foodists
may not get enough.
Being underweight, along
with nutritional deficiencies,
can cause women
to lose their period
and could contribute
to osteoporosis.
Those eating 100 percent raw
can become too skinny.
And as many as half
may stop their period.
Does this actually have
an effect on bone mass?
Raw foodists had significantly
lower bone mineral density
throughout
their entire skeleton,
and specifically
in their spine and hips.
There are a number
of seriously flawed myths
that circulate
within the raw foods community,
like we need to consume
live plant enzymes
which are deactivated
by cooking.
Well, they're deactivated
by our stomach acid, too.
And since we're not plants,
we have no need
for plant enzymes.
Our body makes all
the enzymes we need to function
from the protein we eat.
If, for whatever reason,
you want to eat 100 percent raw,
first, you must take
a B12 supplement
so you don't get
other nutrient deficiencies.
Study Davis and Melina's
comprehensive guide
on the subject.
Also, a diet based
on modern cultivated fruits
is not nutritionally adequate.
They're a pale shadow
of the wild fruits
eaten by our ape ancestors.
Make sure you rinse
the natural acids off your teeth
after eating sour
fruits and beverages
so you don't erode
your dental enamel.
And also, make sure you
sufficiently chew your food
so you don't block
your digestive tract.
In fact, we explicitly recommend
against raw food diets
for young children,
as they just don't have
the stomach capacity
to get adequate nutrition.
Although an all-raw food diet
can be healthy
(this raw triple-ironman
showed no signs
of dietary deficiencies
or impaired health),
there is no reliable evidence
to suggest that
it's more healthful
than a diet of whole plant
foods--cooked or not.